this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
hi all welcome to this episode of
software engineering radio today we have
Arun Gupta discussing open source
strategy and Community Aaron holds the
position of vice president and general
manager of open ecosystems initiatives
at Intel Corporation
Arun has over two decades of experience
as an open source strategist Advocate
and practitioner he has successfully
guided companies like apple Amazon and
Sun Microsystems in adopting open source
principles welcome to the show Arun is
there anything else you'd like to add to
the bio before we get started
no um I'm super happy to be here and
very excited awesome so our goal today
is to really drill into have big Tech
participates in the open source
ecosystem and I'd really like to first
start with telling our listeners about
some episodes that we have that they
might want to listen to that handle and
talk about open source these are episode
94 on open source business models
episode 327 on developer productivity
and episode 192 on open source
development perspectives
so can we start with the business model
and the business case
why does big Tech participate in the
open source ecosystem
yeah
done open source at a wide range of
companies you know companies like apple
Amazon sun which are really big tech
companies and rather smaller company
like couch base you know their business
cases are very different and I've seen
very clearly that the reason that they
participate in open source
it only sustains if it is very clearly
tied to the business case
take a look at Amazon for example right
at Amazon I was part of the open source
strategy team where I was on the loan to
different service teams helping them
build and craft their open source
strategy
so to begin with I was with the
containers team you know this is the
time when we were starting Amazon eks
Amazon eks is directly built on top of
kubernetes so it's very essential very
critical that we participate in the
kubernetes community because the issues
that Amazon was facing at that point of
time were very specific to Amazon
because you're building a managed
service the scale is very different the
problems are very unique and so in an
open source community
you can't just file a bug and say
somebody else will fix it up there is no
magical Community the magical Community
actually consists of all these people
from these different vendors that are
making the community move forward so you
have to understand the social dynamics
you have to understand what are the key
players in the community what is it that
is of priority in the community just
like you know any other commercial
entity you got to do that in your own
company but now you got to do that in a
very open transparent manner in the
community
and that's sort of the strategy is what
I was building for Amazon's Amazon you
know is very customer obsessed company
in that sense they were contributing to
the open source projects where their
customers wanted them to be successful
so more often than not they will create
Integrations with their existing
services and that's where they will
contribute to the open source project so
that
pick an open source project you know
MySQL postgres kubernetes Kafka
Cassandra they will make that run on a
scale in order to run it on their scale
they need to make sure there is no
technical debt inside Amazon and all the
work that they're doing is contributed
Upstream so that it stays up in the
community as well so that's the reason
Amazon was doing it if you think in
terms of Apple
the reason Apple was contributing to
open sources because
a lot of open services at Apple runs
using Java so they need to make sure
that they can bring in the latest
changes from java and run it in the most
optimal manner a lot of the services
rather than kubernetes same thing you
know you don't want to maintain an
internal Fork if kubernetes has more
than 4 000 Developers
rather more than 60 000 contributors
coming from over 4000 companies you
can't have that level of engineering
resource inside the company and the core
product of Apple is very different so it
helps them with that undifferentiated
heavy lifting that let's bring that
Collective wisdom Collective power
Collective knowledge of the community
and bring it in home and then leverage
it
ninety percent of the job is already
done out there we just need to do 10
percent more as opposed to doing it
in-house let's do that in the community
so that we can continue to leverage the
latest Innovation that is happening in
the community
here I'm at Intel
Intel has been a long time contributor
to open source for over 20 years
actually you know just about the time
you know that I was joining the open
source movement so they've been doing it
longer than that as a matter of fact
our primary Intel is a silicon company
and the primary means our customers
consume our product which is a Intel
silicon whether it's in the client in
the edge in the data center in the
private Cloud whatever
the primary means that consume it is
using all of these open source projects
hundreds of Open Source projects so in
order for them
to make sure that that open source
project continues to run in the most
optimized manner that's exactly the
reason Intel contributes to these open
source projects because we have new
instruction set coming out you know in a
chip we have new features coming out in
the chat we want to make sure like those
features are available in Linux kernel
in open jdk which is a Java reference
implementation in pie torch in
tensorflow and Cassandra in Kafka you
pick a project Intel contributes to 300
plus such projects so
if you see the primary reason these
companies
just like Intel is contributing is to be
aligned with their business case and
that's the only way I've seen it sustain
you know there are places where I've
seen where you are contributing on the
fringes and it stays on the fringes and
it doesn't become either your strategy
or a culture is sort of a tactic you
know to to handle it and I'm really
excited that I am at Intel here because
you know the leadership truly gets it
that why we contribute to open ecosystem
why it matters to us okay makes sense
you mentioned Community knowledge so
that's adding to the knowledge of people
within the company
so it's intellectual knowledge but what
about intellectual property
yeah so I mean if you think about it you
know and that's where you think in terms
of intellectual knowledge versus
intellectual property so
if you're doing a closed source project
you're more likely to have
a seamless streamline experience you got
to figure out some value that you're
adding as part of that closed source
project and that is probably your IP
that is where you file an intellectual
property but the part that I really
enjoy about open source Community is
sort of building that intellectual
knowledge
and that's not just inside the company
that's really outside the company
the example of kubernetes once again now
the fact that there are over 4 000
companies 60 000 contributors you know
giving back to kubernetes what that
means is the knowledge the intellectual
knowledge is spread across that many
companies
now if I need a SRE skill set if I need
a development skill set if I need some
other skill set in kubernetes that is
more likely already available what that
means is there are so many blogs there
are so many horror stories there are so
many War Stories there are so many
debugging stories there are so many
tools there is such a wide large
ecosystem that is available so I'm
really tapping into that intellectual
knowledge whereas opposed to
intellectual property which is only a
few people inside my company knows but
with intellectual knowledge you're
really tapping into that wide range of
YouTube tutorials stack Overflow posts
conference talks blog posts which
generally is not possible if you're
holding on to the intellectual property
because you are the only one that knows
about it I think that Community
Collective knowledge is really really
fundamental here which is what allows
you to move at a faster pace
so you also added so as we're discussing
the why you've also added the
availability of talent so relation to
hiring to the business case sounds like
while we're on the why can we talk about
security
something that I've heard on many
discussions on open source is that
it's open source code is more secure and
one of the reasons is that it has many
eyeballs and the more the eyeballs the
less the bugs
and hence vulnerabilities are likely to
be discovered and fixed quickly by the
community how true is that
the number of eyeballs can vary a lot
depending on the code basis isn't that
true
that is very true and this is actually
what you quoted is just the leanness's
law which basically says given
significant number of eyeballs on a code
base all bugs are shallow and that's
what this really refers to if you think
about yes I mean that is absolutely the
nature you know if it's a hobby project
of mine that only I am maintaining them
I am the only eyeball then that's not
gonna improve the quality of the bug
because that is only one narrow
parochial perspective as opposed to look
at something like Linux kernel uh look
at something like kubernetes that
diversity that inclusive nature of the
project that as they say
in open source we stand on the shoulder
of giants you know and the giants like
you know for a project like kubernetes
are companies like Google and red hat
and Microsoft and the Intel and Amazon
and all because each of these are
scratching their specific itch each of
these is truly saying that okay here are
the concerns that matter to our
customers we're going to fix it and then
they are doing that in a very Collective
manner out there and it's not just
feature development so what that means
is if there is a cve or a vulnerability
happening they are looking into that
deeply each of these companies for as a
matter of fact have a deep security team
like I know at Intel we have a very as a
matter of fact literally last earlier
this week actually I was reading an
article by Forbes where Intel is voted
as the most cyber secure company so we
have a very deep security team and when
we are looking at sort of that
code for kubernetes we look at it from
that very deep angle and if there is a
vulnerability that occurs in any of the
open source projects most of the open
source projects do have a very clearly
defined security mechanism process that
is a vulnerability before we make a
public disclosure let's send it to the
vulnerability disclosure list so that we
give
an opportunity for the project to fix
the vulnerability and once you are able
to fix it then you can announce it and
release it and that hey here's the
vulnerability found here is what is
patched so that effectively in the
downstream distros which is like the
other managed distribution of the open
source project they can fix it up as
well so I truly believe that more
eyeballs make all bugs shallow because
is that Devil's perspective you know go
back to the intellectual knowledge
because
everybody has that unique perspective
that they care about and when they look
at the particular bug fix they're truly
looking at it from their perspective and
every grammatical mistake that is
updated in that open source project
makes that open source project that much
better so I think that is truly how it
operates
so the the way you describe it it's very
intentional it takes a lot of management
it takes a lot of process to build us so
let's talk about the how next so you
mentioned open source culture within the
company
and then strategy too how do you
contrast those two
yeah a lot of companies can have a
strategy for open source that or we have
open source strategy which is sort of
the top down the CEO says so or the in
case of a startup company the governing
VC say so or the board operator say so
but unless there is a culture in the
company that
is not going to happen and let me
explain that a little bit more you might
have heard that quote which says culture
eats strategy for breakfast so no matter
what your strategy is if the culture is
not there if the processes are not I
mean as they say right willpower is
overrated you know you can have a
willpower for whatever you want to do
but unless there are mechanisms that are
built into the company that truly
enfolds that
enforce is the wrong word but that truly
enable that open source methodologies
you're not going to be successful over
there and by that that's exactly what
the culture is where you know
Engineers are incentivized to do open
source work they are given time to do
open source work they are given time to
really help out in the community you
know in an open source Community code is
often considered as their glorious work
but that's probably 10 percent of the
effort you know 90 percent of the effort
really is about the non-glorious work
where you know somebody got to review
the pull request somebody got to put the
code so somebody has to fix the dog
somebody has to triage the issue
somebody has to do the project
management you know somebody like
kubecon is happening you know at kubecon
Amsterdam there were what 10 000
developers remember somebody's running
that show a lot of it is supported by
Linux Foundation but
then if you think about it somebody has
to review the talk somebody has to
create the tracks uh somebody has to you
know make sure all other things happen
as well and that's again that is
something done by the volunteers of the
community so there's a lot of chop wood
carry water work and my point is if that
culture is not there in the company
where I mean I am on the cncf governing
board I'm the chairperson as well so a
good part of my time goes towards that
role there are lots of people from Intel
that are in loss of leadership positions
like Kathy Zhang is on the cncf
technical oversight committee Marlo
Weston he is the cncf tax sustainability
co-chair you know a probe is on the open
ssf uh technical advisory Council and
now chair as well these are non-code
jobs but that truly requires you to be
out there in the community and do the
work unless there is support from the
management and that's exactly the
cultural piece of it so Pat might say
open ecosystem matters to us but it
truly truly truly kind of falls down
from Pat to Greg to everybody in the
management chain that is the culture if
that culture doesn't happen if that
culture doesn't exist no matter what
your strategy is
so let's say effort is made to create
that culture developers are given time
encouraged
how do you sustain that what else do you
do to make sure that that continues
yeah a bunch of things that really need
to happen for example open source
program office you know if your company
doesn't have an open source program
office highly highly recommend to get
that set up and truly the main purpose
of that open source program office is to
create that open source culture we of
course do the compliance they do the
license verification they make sure that
the open source coming into the company
and the open source going out of the
company is dealt in a reasonable manner
so all of those not a reason in the
right manner so all of those things are
really truly done by osbo or the open
source program office or SPO also kind
of helps you create
that processes inside the company really
where they can talk to different
business units that hey you're trying to
do this in open source manner
here is how the right thing to do is you
know and they build that they truly
enable that culture inside the company
and I would highly recommend if you have
an ospo or if you don't have an ospo and
want to get started with it take a look
at the to-do Group by Linux Foundation
they have a very extensive guide on how
your hospital could look like where
could the hospital sit like what the
size of the hospital would be what the
charter of the Oscar should be all of
those are in details kind of highlighted
as part of that
so you mentioned some of the open source
foundations I believe you mentioned uh
OS SF or open source security Foundation
can you talk a little bit about this one
and you know what is the purpose and how
does the company collaborate with them
to Inc maybe to improve the security
posture yeah absolutely now foundations
play a critical role you know to build
that open source culture the foundations
is where a lot of the Leading Edge work
happens so if you think about kubernetes
the project kubernetes is part of the
cncf foundation that Foundation was
created over seven years ago Intel has
been part of the cncf foundation from
the very beginning Linux Foundation has
gosh over 700 plus projects across
multiple foundations so similarly there
is Apache Foundation you know we talked
about open source security foundation so
there are a lot of these foundations now
typically if you take a look at the
foundation Foundation we'll have a
governing board that is responsible for
the administrative Financial aspect of
the foundation and then there is a
technical committee which would really
provide the technical guidance and the
direction to the foundation itself Now
intel is part of over 700 plus
foundations and standard bodies and they
range from a very wide you know I mean
all the way from
Intel is a big company so we have we
really truly think from all the way from
Silicon to application so we are part of
lots and lots of Hardware standard
foundations and all the way to app
foundations as well so
and it and as I said we have leadership
positions in both sides you know we are
I myself on the cncf governing board and
the chair of the governing board I'm on
the open ssf governing board as well and
I also help out with the Linux
Foundation governing board in addition I
mentioned a few names Dan Middleton as a
matter of fact is part of the
confidential Computing technical
advisory Council and he's a chair for
that and the other names I mentioned
already so there are lots and lots of
people who are out there and the reason
it's important to join these foundations
because it truly allows you to be on the
Leading Edge of what that needs to be
done around uh in in the technology
landscape that's where all of the work
is happening that's where your
networking with your peers with your
customers in the industry and that
really helps you define where the
technology is gonna go and the reason
Intel participates in these foundations
and standard bodies is truly to
represent our customers interest over
there we truly believe that you know our
customers Hold Us responsible for making
sure the direction that the technology
is taking is going to meet their
interest and we also need to align it
with our business interests that's the
reason we participate in all of this now
specifically about openssf uh yup Intel
has been part of it for a very long time
the foundation is about three years old
so we have been very much part of it
from the beginning I am on the governing
board as I mentioned probe is on the
technical advisory Council and the chair
of the technical advisory Council
Catherine Ruckman is on the marketing
committee and the co-chair of it as well
so we have a few leadership positions
here where we are truly trying to make
sure we take the foundation forward
working with the rest of our colleagues
and partners in the foundation itself
the main Charter of the open ssf
foundation is truly to improve the
security posture of Open Source So to
that extent they have several projects
that they have done and the most visible
project that you would probably have
heard of is the open ssf scorecard uh
what it does is it takes a look at your
GitHub project and then it'll tell you
what your open source security posture
kind of look at look look like and then
it will take a look at multiple elements
of your project and then it'll give you
a scorecard and the scorecard varies
from 0 to 10 and then it gives you
recommendations that oh you know what it
gives you a detailed report that why
your scorecard is in a certain number
and what are the missing pieces for that
so it truly gives you very specific
detailed information that in order to
improve your score here is how you
should take a look at it and here is
what you need to do so it truly works in
that direction
um lost and loss of similar discussions
happening within openssf and it's quite
an exciting time honestly something else
that openssf also defined last year we
had a meeting with the at the White
House for open source security Summit
particularly with the given the
presidential mandate on the security
given the log for Jay debacle that
happened and so they Define our 10 point
work stream
essentially an open ssf scorecard is one
of those work streams that came out of
that work stream but there are these 10
point work streams that are looking at
it
how do we improve the CI CD how do we
improve the package managers how do we
improve the education how do we improve
the enablement so it's truly looking at
it in a holistic manner so really that
10 point work stream Buy open ssf and
driving that in the future direction is
like really the way to go
that's very interesting very very
educational thank you for that so can
any open source project owner submit
their project to get the scorecard to
open SSL yeah absolutely so open SSL
scorecard is open GitHub repo they have
GitHub actions all sorts of stuff you
can just clone the repo or you can just
use a GitHub action really bring the
GitHub action as part of your GitHub
project and that really allows you to
kind of generate the source scorecard
and say here is my scorecard and then
take a look at the report and then say
how can I improve that
do the open source foundation help with
establishing other standards as well
absolutely well if you think about it
the
process has evolved over the years right
about 15 20 years ago those the standard
bodies are still relevant like w3c os's
those are still very relevant but over a
period of time what has happened is
standards have their place but
kubernetes is not the digital standard
but it's a de facto standard what I mean
by that is there is use so widely so
pervasively similarly Docker is not a
standard but is the de facto standard if
you're building a container application
that means you know people would use the
word container and Docker synonymously
so by that I mean is that the
Technologies are so widely available and
used that you know
that's where you know foundations like
cncf have become very relevant because
what they're saying is
not a standard but it is a standard in
that sense I think in that sense yes it
very well helps Define let's think of it
this let's think of a common way by
which different vendors have agreed to
create a compute layer right because
that is for the benefit of the customer
not necessarily a standard but still
very commonly very heavily adapted all
across the board
so what you really reference to is
creating framework or a platform for
collaboration between vendors so one of
the things that I've had in mind
recently is the use of kubernetes and
maybe it's not standards but best
practices
for let's say use by SAS applications
right I couldn't find a lot of material
on that as an example
especially you know discussing is it
better to run multi-tenant single tenant
so where is that kind of discussion
facilitated by some of these foundations
or other methodologies maybe firstly
writing events or any other ways of
encouraging collaboration yeah
absolutely I mean that is really you
know one of the core Focus areas for
these foundations if you think about it
now you talk about events so let's get
to that in a second but before that you
know one of the things that cncf does is
there are focus groups for example there
are six where folks of different
interests similar interests rather they
gather together so for example there is
end user working group you know or say
not a Sig really but end user community
in cncf now these are customers who are
using Cloud native technology as opposed
to being a vendor of a cloud native
technology so I was at Amazon Amazon is
a vendor of a cloud native technology
very much like Intel because we sell
chips where Cloud native applications
run
apple on the other hand is a end user of
native technology so they bring these
end users together and these end users
can then truly discuss like
I don't want to see when their pictures
or sales pitch is here I truly just want
to hear what end user concerns are what
tools are you using what technologies
are you using so those kind of
discussions happen
um lastly um last time when I was at
qcon Amsterdam there was a discussion
about how do we run Edge native
application using Cloud native you know
so that's again like a special interest
group where people are talking about
how do I bring kubernetes to the edge
what does it take what are the concerns
are they similar you know because on
edge your memory compute footprint is
very different than data center so how
about the concerns different so I think
that becomes a very interesting
conversation so these foundations truly
bring given the fact there are 10 000
people at kubecon Amsterdam
their people are all different kind of
interest and they create their own
self-farming communities where they talk
about these things
events is exactly
how they enable it uh a lot of the
discussion I would say happen online
because it's such a global phenomena
essentially but events is truly becoming
an anchor Point like you know if you
think in terms of the kubernetes
community
there's a kubecon that happens in North
America which happened in Detroit last
year happening in Chicago this year
there is a kubecon that happens in
Europe happens in Amsterdam a couple of
months ago happening in Paris next year
and then kubecon is also going back to
Shanghai this year so think of these as
three different big geographies where
people will gather together you know and
in addition to that there are this
kubernetes community days that happens
you know that are organized by local
folks you know a little bit smaller as
opposed to 10 000 people maybe 500
people get together in multiple cities
so enabling that is super important and
I would say equally important is running
these events inside your company because
given the economic climate not everybody
is allowed or able to travel to all of
these fancy places so that's where
running those internal events building
that internal Community is super
important
like at Intel we did the open ecosystem
Summit a couple of months ago
we had over 2500 people that joined that
Opel ecosystem Summit and what that
enabled us is we are talking to anybody
and everybody that is doing open
ecosystem work at Intel and truly will
be able to talk to each other we have a
lot of self-farming communities as I was
talking about external events nothing
happens internally as well but that
happens a lot more freely because now
you are within the company constraints
and you can talk a lot more openly
because when you're externally then you
can talk only so much things that needs
to be approved and all that stuff but in
the company there is a little bit more
Freedom so to say I'm not saying that
you can talk completely freely but there
is a little bit more Freedom by which
you can share those things you can look
at the logs you can look at the source
code all of that I think as much as
external events are important it's super
important to continue with the internal
events as well
it's interesting so now you're talking
internal events within the company so
I'm wondering can other best practices
of Open Source be brought to closed
Source has Intel done that
absolutely I think one of the key
elements of that is sort of the inner
Source part of it
so if you think about open source there
are a lot of good practices out there
like how
people collaborate together you know how
there is a common code base you know how
companies that are competing for the
same space but truly are co-operating
you know in the open source space what
that means is they are collaborating but
yet competing on their own
implementation element of it how there
is test driven methodology you know how
there is common CI CD mechanism by which
anybody can submit a pull request how
there is a governance model that
not one company will have all the
maintainers but the maintainers are
Diversified truly across multiple
companies so those are some of the
really good practices of Open Source
community
and if you bring those inside your
company that truly becomes your inner
Source element and Intel has done that
very effectively over the years I would
say over the last few years we have
truly been focusing on building that
inner Source Community essentially and
that inner Source Community truly allows
us
to improve the discoverability of the
code inside the company and by that what
I mean is really
let's say a team needs to solve a
particular problem they don't have to
start from it from ground up because we
have a unified CI CD system across the
company and a particular naming
mechanism oh I want to start
infrastructure application in this
domain and you search into that common
code base and you can see what work is
happening in that space and you can say
ah you know what this project already
serves maybe 60 to 80 percent of my need
and if I just put maybe one or two
maintainers on that project by looking
at the governance model
it could be very effective very much
like open source but just inside the
company it improves the descriptability
and because you are running inside the
company it also becomes your single
point by which you can incorporate a lot
of good hygiene you can improve the
security posture things like open ssf
scorecard could be injected into that
CID CD system where not every project
has to do it by themselves you just
because it's a unified CI CD if you just
update the CI CD system one Boom
everybody is now automatically getting
their scorecard you can start telling
them about you know s-bomb generation
for example right you know not everybody
has to worry about as bomb generation we
know the language that you're using
we're going to inject this as part of
your CI CD Pipeline and boom the s-bomb
generation is happening or at least
we'll tell you that if you're not doing
s-bomb generation so I think you can
really bring a lot of good hygiene as
part of that and truly bringing the best
of Open Source practices inside the
company and Intel has done that changes
over the last few years and we have a
long road ahead of us we're very excited
in terms of how this road looks like
so how do you start with encouraging
developers to participate either in the
structure you've created within the
company or for open source is there a
prescribed methodology or a path or you
wait for developers to approach the
program office
yeah no I think it really goes back and
forth you know as I was talking about
you could do sort of little fires around
the company where you're doing this in
your own Silo and your corn corner but
truly when it makes a difference is when
like
a leader of a big big unit business unit
says we're gonna go all in on this are
we gonna take this as a methodology that
truly truly helps
and in that sense I consider myself very
lucky because in my management chain all
the way up to pack I don't have to
explain what open ecosystem is my
management chain is pushing me to define
a better definition of open ecosystem
how do we do better how do we push the
boundaries how do we make this work for
Intel and for our customers in that
sense I think that really goes a long
way
doing those internal events as I was
talking about the open ecosystem Summit
with 2500 developers from all across the
company they truly start discovering
that you know what there are so many
like-minded people who are actually
thinking on the same lines and is really
breaking that ice by doing that event
a couple of months ago we also did
internal open source hackathon really
successful you know we got a very wide
range of Diversified contributors they
were maintainers who were ready to
Mentor other new developers they called
out that okay here is the language we
need here are the skills that we need
here is a good first issue that you can
fix let us walk you through what that
Journey would look like and the reason
it becomes very incentivate is a good
incentive for a new developer is because
you can practice that inner Source skill
inside your company
and that skill is very transferable to
outside so you are practicing that in a
safe zone so to say inside the company
you know because oftentimes the fear
people have is if I'm operating an open
source shoot you know if I do a bad code
I'm going to look bad that's not the
point at all actually no I mean as a
matter of fact that's the beauty of it
you know if you write a bad code people
aren't going to judge you but they're
going to give you feedback and make you
better and if you don't judge yourself
you know then let Lord not others judge
you I think but in that Source kind of
gives you that safe Zone by which you
can practice this I think there are a
lot of ways I've seen across the company
I have done these kind of inner Source
movements at multiple companies and the
hackathons the internal events I've done
at a wide range of companies and I've
always found them to be extremely
successful
I think what you're saying is that as as
developers sometimes
at least in my experience developers
like to have all the answers but I think
what you're kind of saying is that it's
more important to have questions that
you can then discuss with your group not
just within your image a team but first
within the company and then externally
and then build your knowledge base as
well
absolutely right you know because nobody
has answers all the time or any of the
time as a matter of fact
you may know you may think that that may
be your answer but really coming up with
questions is the tough one you know
coming up with the right questions and
maybe you don't know maybe you only know
your end goal that this is where I want
to get to that this is how I aspire to
be and have that discussion
I really apply mindfulness practice over
there you know do that discussion in a
non-judgmental way and that'll take you
a long way that okay you know what this
is what I want to achieve this is what
I've done and if somebody says it's
crappy don't get emotional about it and
I was like yeah okay Scrappy tell me why
it's crappy you know here are three
things broken okay how do I fix those
three things just because you have built
it and somebody is giving you quote
unquote a judgment on it don't feel
emotional about it but you know or don't
feel defensive about it brother emotion
is the wrong word don't feel defensive
about it but say okay tell me how can I
make it better if you approach it that
way one step at a time you know you will
be successful and for new developers my
advice usually is don't have that
imposter syndrome that
my son is doing internship right now at
Disney and literally yesterday night we
were talking about he's saying Dad I'm
working on a very extremely complex code
base and when I look into one part of
the code base it goes to another part
then another part that another part and
I feel weird asking questions to my
mentor I said no that's not the way it
works that's exactly the way it works
rather you have to go ask questions
because if you're not going to ask
questions you're going to go that toilet
Vortex very soon so ask questions
don't be afraid
and honestly as somebody who has
mentored a lot of people I love people
who ask questions because if you ask
questions I generally think that you are
interested and you care about the
project
makes a lot of sense so let's
focus a little bit on a lot of things
you said about Intel so you talked about
300 plus Community managed projects and
I think you mentioned membership in more
than 700 foundations and standards
bodies
how does Intel then measure the return
on this investment is there a way or is
just organic over the years you've seen
benefits
you know for the last several like
several decades as a matter of fact and
what Intel is committed to is to drive
collaboration standardization and
interoperability in open source software
from the beginning and we truly believe
in catalyzing community Innovation among
developers there's a letter that Pat
gelsinger wrote about nine months after
he joined the company and he and he said
that he has a strong bias for open
source and when I read that letter I was
like dude that I wish that was my CEO I
was not part of Intel at that point of
time but that truly struck a chord with
me he talked about how and why open
ecosystem matters you know because it
truly allows you to build trust deliver
choice and ensure interoperability from
our industry
we are the largest corporate contributor
to Linux kernel since 2007. that is the
reason we continue to contribute because
we have truly seen that when we make
contribution to the Upstream kernel from
there it goes to Midstream kernels like
Ubuntu for example and then from there
it goes to Downstream kernel like
canonical which is an actual
distribution and I was at I was in China
last week there are lots and lots of
Midstream kernels like open Euler open
analysis open Cloud OS then lost the
loss of Midstream kernels over there and
they all pick their optimizations from
the upstream and the fact that Intel is
contributing to Upstream that truly
allows us to scale that I don't have to
work with each and every vendor and give
them our optimization we just push our
optimization upstream and voila it just
spreads out from there to all of the
Midstream and the downstream
distribution same thing with open jdk
Java has over 12 million developers
around the world I know and how do we
reach out to these developers and make
sure that when they are running jdk on
the latest Intel platform is super
optimized it's the most optimized jdk
that they've ever ever experienced with
so we have our open jdk team that
contributes all of those optimizations
straight to the main branch of open jdk
open source
from there it goes to the downstream
distribution whether it's an oracle jdk
whether it's Amazon correcto or Eclipse
adoption doesn't matter so the Intel
optimizations are available over there
pytots verify same thing pytos doesn't
have a downstream distribution but we
contribute all our optimizations to
pytorch Upstream literally this morning
I learned that
pytorch you know we have multiple
maintainers in the pytos main project
but this morning I learned that we had a
darkathon that was just done recently
and several Intel folks were recognized
as part of the darkathan and that's the
chop wood carry water work I was talking
about so we have truly seen direct
benefits our customer telling us that
hey you know what we have run this open
source project or this distribution on
Intel hardware and we believe it runs
the best over there the total cost is
the best for us and that's why we enjoy
this and that's why we're going to keep
investing into it and expand our
footprint so
we call that as a silicon pull through
Revenue that the reason we are investing
in these open source projects because
then customers use the downstream
distribution and then they're buying
more and more silicon from us I think it
makes that total business sense and
that's why Pat and Greg lavender and our
CTO keeps talking about and why we want
to invest in the open ecosystem
community
in addition to that
you know
we believe that the community-led
projects that benefit everyone not just
Intel
you know and that truly goes back to
what Intel has been all along
sounds very very interesting so on that
note can you share maybe what Intel has
planned for the years ahead maybe the
immediate year ahead is there any key
changes or open source initiatives that
into I was watching out for
yeah no I mean we are always on the
lookout for what is the latest and the
greatest happening in the industry uh
Intel like we have been involved with
all of these Foundation standard bodies
open source projects you know pie charts
continues to gain more momentum so we
are definitely keeping our investment
only adding more people over there
hopefully we are definitely looking to
engage more in the AI element of it
Intel is committed to the true
democratization of AI from the cloud to
the network and to the Edge by enabling
broader access to Solutions and more
cost effective deployments through an
open ecosystem approach when we talk to
our customers they tell us that they
don't like the closed approach of Cuda
and we believe that open ecosystem that
truly allows you to run your open source
software on a platform of your choice
you know on and by that I mean a CPU or
a GPU or xpu no matter where it is so we
want to make sure that along with
delivering heterogeneous architectures
for AI workloads Intel also delivers
also offers actually Advanced software
as well as investment in a holistic
end-to-end systems level approach to AI
software I think that's definitely where
you're going to see a lot more
communication from Intel
and we have we of course have Intel
Innovation coming up in September we
continue to participate in all the major
open source events we continue to
participate in the partner events for
example I spoke at Microsoft build a
month ago we talked about uh how Intel
and Microsoft are partnering on
confidential Computing so I think you
will continue to see a lot more emphasis
on AI security open ecosystem approach
you know that continues to be a very key
element of what Intel has been all along
so how can our listeners follow this
progress how can they maybe follow you
and maybe even contact you yeah
absolutely
open.intel.com is the team website where
you can learn anything and everything
about open ecosystem essentially you can
also follow us at open at Intel that is
a Twitter handle where we tweet
regularly about our event presences our
blog posts our podcast appearances
wherever we are going you know if you
want to connect with us in person you
can always send them a message if you
want to talk you can always reach out to
me my DMs are open on Twitter one word
so shoot me a message I always love to
hear from listeners see what they like
what they don't like what would they
like to hear more about so we're always
listening for that feedback
Aaron is there any topic today that
you'd like to cover that we have not
about that briefly where we said open
source really stands on the shoulder of
giants
if you are getting new into in the
industry or if you are relatively new to
the industry don't be afraid
I give you the power to stand up and ask
all those questions because we truly
want to enable the next generation of
developers I'm happy to Mentor I'm happy
to advise I'm happy to guide you know
just like me there are lots and lots of
people who are in the open source
community that are very kind very
generous and very helpful so consider
this as an open invitation to the open
source Community come join us we cannot
do this without you
thank you so much Aaron this was very
interesting and very educational I hope
our listeners enjoy it as well
thank you so much for having me here
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC
radio.slack.com you can also email us at
team sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening